Finding Aid for the Joseph Chouinard Collection of Scores, 1951-1993
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Joseph Chouinard Collection of Scores, 1951-1993
Mus. Arc. 71.3
Chouinard, Joseph Jerod, 1926-2014
1 box (33 folders)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The collection contains scores of 33 musical works by composer, singer, and librarian Joseph Chouinard.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Joseph Chouinard, 2006.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
Joseph Chouinard was born in Middletown, Connecticut. His birth certificate lists his middle name as Gerard and his date of birth as May 4th, 1926. However, later documentation shows his date of birth to be May 7th, 1926 and his middle name to be Jerod. It is unclear why this discrepancy exists, though it should be noted. He graduated from Middletown High School in 1944. Following graduation Joseph enlisted in the United States Navy. He served in the Navy from 1944-1946, during which time he was stationed in Okinawa, Japan. After he was discharged he attended the University of Connecticut, graduating with a BA in Music in 1950. He stayed at the university and in 1952, obtained his Master of Arts and Music Degree. Later, he obtained his MLS in Music Librarianship from State University of New York College at Geneseo in 1970. In addition to his degrees, Joseph studied with Nadia Boulanger at Fontainebleau in 1957 and 1958. He also attended the 1961 Session of the Summer School for Singers in Oxford, England.
Throughout his life, Joseph performed both nationally and internationally as a bass baritone. He performed both as a chorus member and as a soloist, including performances at the Tanglewood Festival, Calvary Church in New York City, the Tri-Cities Opera Company in Binghamton, the Aspen Music Festival, the Florida International Music Festival, Columbia University, Arundel Opera (Maine), Theatre Under the Stars in Atlanta, Georgia, and with the University Opera Studio at the State University of New York at Buffalo.
His music librarianship career included positions as Music and Art Librarian, California State College at San Bernardino (1971-1974), Music Cataloger, State University of New York at Buffalo (1974-1978), Music Librarian, State University of New York College at Fredonia (1978-1991), and Exchange Music Librarian at Royal Holloway College, Great Britain (1983-1984). After retiring, Joseph Chouinard remained active as a volunteer at the State University of New York at Buffalo Music Library and at the Buffalo Veterans Administration Hospital where he led patients in various arts activities such as readings of plays and poetry. He died in Buffalo on January 6th, 2014.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of scores of 33 musical works by Joseph Chouinard. The majority of the works are choral settings, some on words by Chouinard.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in one series alphabetically by title.
Container List
- Alleluya for soprano solo and choir, unaccompanied, June - October 1982, 1 pencil holograph score (22 pages) and 1 ink holograph (22 pages) (Box 1, Folder 01)
- Before the earth had yet begun, 2 February 1986, 1 ink and pencil holograph score (20 pages); For four-part choir with organ accompaniment. Hymn text by Reverend T. Herbert O'Driscoll, Calgary, 1985. (Box 1, Folder 02)
- Christmas introit, 11 January 1983, 1 pencil holograph score (3 leaves); For four-part unaccompanied choir. First line of text: Christ is born today. (Box 1, Folder 03)
- A dance (for Ruth P.), undated, 1 ink manuscript violin part; For unknown combination. Only the violin part is extant. (Box 1, Folder 04)
- Drumming, 6 February 1989, 1 pencil manuscript score (11 leaves); For 3 parts. (Box 1, Folder 05)
  Includes 1 leaf of performance instructions. The title was changed from Clapping to Drumming.
- God's love for us, and our love for Jesus (Introit III), 2 April 1984, 1 pencil and ink holograph score (9 pages) and 1 ink holograph score (9 pages); For unaccompanied choir: Soprano, soprano, alto, tenor, bass. First line of text: God's love has laid hold of us. (Box 1, Folder 06)
  Includes 1 ink manuscript leaf of the complete text, dated 18 March 1984.
- Hodie Christus natus est, 14 November 1979, 1 photocopy of holograph score (1 leaf), 1 mimeograph copy of holograph score (1 leaf), and 1 photoreproduction of typeset score (3 leaves); For unaccompanied four-part choir. Annotation in caption on mimeograph: Performed at Royal Holloway College, Egham, Surrey, U.K. Dec. 1983 (9th). Copied by Dr. Pike for use by the College Choir. Performed Christmas even in Wimbledon (Catholic Church) Dec. 1983. Inscription in caption of photocopy score: With many thanks, Lionel Pike. (Box 1, Folder 07)
  Includes printed schedule for performances in the Royal Holloway College Chapel, December 1983.
- Introit II, 4 October 1983, 1 ink holograph score (7 pages), 1 ink holograph score (6 pages), 1 photocopy of holograph score (1 leaf); For unaccompanied four-part choir. First line of text: The very thought of you, Jesus. Text by Chouinard after Edward Bairstow's setting of similar words. Caption on photocopy: Dedicated to L. J. Pike and choir, Royal Holloway College, Egham, Surrey, U.K. and inscribed With very many thanks, Lionel Pike. (Box 1, Folder 08)
  Includes 1 ink holograph leaf with full text.
- An invocation, July 1981, 1 pencil holograph score (3 pages); For tenor solo and chorus (SATB), unaccompanied. First line of text: From the light within the mind of God. (Box 1, Folder 09)
  Includes two other works: Chorale for organ, August 1981 (1 page) and Chro-matters for organ, July 1981 (4 pages) and typescript leaf of the text for An invocation.
- The Lord is in His holy temple, Summer 1954, 1 photoreproduction of manuscript score (1 leaf); For four-part unaccompanied chorus. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- May the grace of Christ our savior, 2 December 1980, 1 pencil holograph score (4 pages) and 1 ink holograph score (5 pages); For tenor solo and unaccompanied choir (SATB). Words by John Newton. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Includes photocopy of another unidentified setting of the same hymn tune.
- Nowe let us syng and merry be, 25 November 1981, 1 pencil holograph score (1 leaf); For two voices and tambourine. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- O Western wind, October 1985, 1 pencil and ink holograph score (7 pages) and 1 ink holograph score (7 pages); For unaccompanied six-part chorus. First line of text: O Western wind when wilt thou blow? Dedicated to the Western Wind Ensemble. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Includes photocopy (1 leaf) of printed text.
- O wondrous interchange, 19 June 1985, 1 pencil holograph score (7 pages) and 1 ink holograph score (7 pages); For organ and four-part choir. First line of text: Admirabile commercium, Creator humani. For Ron Martin and his choir. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Includes typescript (1 leaf) of English translation of the text and a photocopy of the Gregorian chant setting of the text in the Liber Usualis.
- Orison hymn, March 1953, 1 pencil manuscript score (1 leaf); For unaccompanied four-part choir. First line of text: God be merciful unto us. For Jack Ossewaarde and Calvary Choir, New York City. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Piece for bassoon and percussion, 19 February 1988, 1 pencil holograph score (8 pages) and 1 pencil manuscript score (12 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Piece for harpsichord, 7 January 1973, 1 pencil holograph score 2 pages), 1 ink holograph score (3 pages), 1 ink manuscript score (2 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Piece for trumpet, piano, and lyra, August 1993, 1 ink holograph score (19 pages) and three ink manuscript parts; Dedicated to T. F. Score in spiral-bound music notebook. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Piece for viola and piano, June 1987, 1 photocopy of holograph score (7 pages), 1 ink holograph part (12 pages), and 1 pencil manuscript part (10 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  The score is for the second movement only. The ink holograph part is for viola. The pencil part is for the first and third movements of the viola part only.
- Prayer, November 1951, 1 ink manuscript score (4 pages); For unaccompanied four-part choir. First line of text: Hear thou our prayer. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Prayer, September 1953, 1 mimeographed copy of manuscript score (2 leaves) and 1 pencil holograph rehearsal piano part (1 leaf); For unaccompanied choir of Soprano I and II and Alto. First line of text: O Domine Deus. Words by Mary, Queen of Scots. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Includes printed program for a performance of the work 16 February 1954 at the Music chapel at Shorter College in Rome, Georgia.
- Psalm 2 excerpt, from Divine Office for Good Friday, January 1982, 1 pencil holograph score (6 pages) and 1 ink manuscript score (4 leaves); For bass and organ. First line of text: Serve the Lord with fear. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Includes photocopy of the printed text.
- Selections, 1978, 1 pencil holograph score (4 pages); On a single folio. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Includes:
  And dance for solo guitar, Fredonia, N.Y. December 1978
  Introit, The Lord is in His Holy temple, for unaccompanied SATB choir, Fredonia, N.Y. 18 September 1978
  After service, (Orison hymn), Lord let thy servants now depart in peace, Fredonia, N.Y. 27 September 1978
  Etude, for solo guitar, Fredonia, N.Y. 24 October 1978
- Show yourself joyful unto the Lord, April 1951, 1 ink manuscript score (3 pages); For unaccompanied four-part choir. Text from Psalm 98. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Song for E. V. (Cats), April 1953, 1 ink manuscript score (3 pages); For voice and piano. First line of text: I recall a night I saw three small cats. Words by Joseph Chouinard. (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Song for Jean T., 1952, 1 ink manuscript score (3 pages), 3 ink manuscript parts (3 pages each), and 3 ink manuscript parts (1 leaf each); For violin, viola, and cello. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Includes 2 sets of parts.
- Spring chorale, 1952, 1 ink manuscript score on vellum (2 leaves), 2 photoreproductions of manuscript score (2 leaves each), 2 ink manuscript parts (1 leaf each); For four-part chorus with viola and flute accompaniment. First line of text: Out come the green things. The two photoreproductions, made from the vellum master, contain different pencil annotations. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Includes printed program for first performance of work on 26 January 1953 recital at Calvary Church, New York City.
- A springtime wish, May 1953, 1 pencil holograph score (3 pages), 1 ink holograph score (5 pages), and 1 pencil holograph score of vocal line (1 leaf); For bass and piano. First line of text: I would I were beneath a tree a-sleeping in the shade. Words by Joseph Chouinard. For P. Treggor. (Box 1, Folder 28)
- String quartet, undated, 4 ink manuscript parts; For two violins, viola, and cello. The parts are marked as the first movement; there is no attribution for composer. (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Sweet potato, 29 November 1984, 1 pencil holograph score (4 leaves); For unidentified instrument or voice with keyboard accompaniment. (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Thanks be to God (Christmas introit), 4 February 1985, 1 pencil and ink holograph score (4 pages); For four-part choir with organ accompaniment. For Ron Martin and his choir (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Vocalise, 1953, 1 ozalid copy of manuscript score (2 pages); For voice and piano. (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Untitled work, January 1952, 1 ink holograph score (5 pages); Either for organ or an ensemble of strings and woodwinds. (Box 1, Folder 33)
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Subjects
Choruses; Instrumental music--Scores and parts; Music--Manuscripts; Chouinard, Joseph Jerod, 1926-2014--Manuscripts
Genres
Scores
Associated Material
Related Resources
Related Resources in the Music Library
Joseph Chouinard Collection of Images
Mus. Arc. 71.2
Contains about 200 photographic prints, 19 slides, and 6 drawings collected by Joseph Chouinard. They provide documentation of his life and career, including his service spent in Okinawa towards the end of World War II.
Joseph Chouinard Papers
Mus. Arc. 71.1
Contains 6 boxes of personal documents, correspondence, concert programs, and clippings.